<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://habitsblog.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://habitsblog.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-05-23T12:22:28+02:00</updated><id>https://habitsblog.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Habitsblog</title><subtitle>Reviewing readings on behaviour and habit-forming.</subtitle><author><name>anonymous</name><email>habitsblog1@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Hacking Bad &amp;amp; Hard Habits - Ch 10 Atomic Habits</title><link href="https://habitsblog.github.io/2019/05/21/atomic10/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hacking Bad &amp; Hard Habits - Ch 10 Atomic Habits" /><published>2019-05-21T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-05-21T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://habitsblog.github.io/2019/05/21/atomic10</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://habitsblog.github.io/2019/05/21/atomic10/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal Context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ynharari.com/book/sapiens/&quot;&gt;sapiens&lt;/a&gt; just like everyone else last year, I was aware of some of the more base instincts and behaviours we display in modern life, and how they can be traced back thousands of years. The way we discuss them in heavier literature however, often comes back down to mating behaviour, the search for nutrition, and avoidance of predators–not why teenaged girls spend all afternoon on &lt;em&gt;facebook&lt;/em&gt;. What I took away from this chapter was how deeply ingrained our motives are for engaging in our habits in a certain way, as well as how modern contexts fit into this picture. The story hasn’t changed! After all these years, we are simply finding different means to the same ends. Knowing all this, I’ve taken a new look at some of my own bad habits, and wondered why I engage in those–what baser desire am I trying to fulfil by browsing reddit, or distracting myself from more pressing issues?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that everyone could do well to look at their daily course of action, even in miniscule things, and try to trace these back to the fundamental desire that they are trying to fulfill. Perhaps with a little bit of additional awareness, we could more easily step outside ourselves and see our habits as independent entities from ourselves. Treating them as manifestations of baser human desire might make it easier to separate these behaviours from our personalities, and work on them as such.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-find-and-fix-the-causes-of-bad-habits&quot;&gt;How to Find and Fix the Causes of Bad Habits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to delve further into this topic, we first need to revisit cravings–what exactly is a craving, actually?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“A craving is a specific manifestation of a deeper underlying motive.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example, as given by Clear: “I want to eat tacos.” is the manifestation of the deeper motive “I need food to survive.”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other examples of underlying motives include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conserve energy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Obtain food and water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find love and reproduce&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Connect and bond with others&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Win social acceptance and approval&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reduce uncertainty&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Achieve status and prestige&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost any product or service centered around the forming of habits (explicitly or implicitly) does not necessarily generate new motivation, but attaches itself to existing &lt;em&gt;underlying motives&lt;/em&gt;. Your craving for cigarettes might be a manifestation of your desire for relief and calm. Playing video games? Achieving status and prestige. As Clear so eloquently puts it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Your habits are modern-day solutions to ancient desires”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though our surroundings, professions, cultures, and gadgets change, the underlying motives behind the behaviour we exhibit remain the same. The crux lies in the fact that there are &lt;strong&gt;many different ways to appease the same underlying motive&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While one person might relieve stress by smoking a cigarette, another might do exactly the opposite and go for a run! As we know, habits go deep–the ones you use to address your cravings are just the ones you have come to know over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your past experiences with the world around you determine how you react to a cue. Every action is subconsciously preceded by a prediction of what will happen next, based solely on your past experience and supplemental information. Two people can look at the same cigarette–one might predict they will be repulsed by the smell, while the other might predict a wave of chemical release and relaxation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We associate certain feelings with these predictions, which we describe as a craving. A craving is described here as the feeling that something is missing, triggered by a cue. The cue alerts you to the fact that there is a discrepancy between your current state, and desired state, upon which you take action to rectify the situation. When you tear open that bag of Doritos, it’s not the cheesy goodness you seek, but rather a &lt;em&gt;different feeling&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To recap: the habits you perform to address the cravings you feel, are attempts to address underlying motives. If that action or habit is successful in addressing that motive, you’ll do it again..and again..and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reprogramming-your-brain-to-enjoy-hard-habits&quot;&gt;Reprogramming Your Brain to Enjoy Hard habits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another tool to make habits more attractive, is simply mentally re-framing them. A slight change in mindset through change in perspective can do wonders to inspire you to chase after a habit more enthusiastically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of it this way, rather than &lt;em&gt;having&lt;/em&gt; to do something, you &lt;em&gt;get&lt;/em&gt; to! Rather than &lt;em&gt;having&lt;/em&gt; to go to the gym, you &lt;em&gt;get&lt;/em&gt; to go out and build beastly strength. Reinterpreting the feeling of dread you get waking up early for work, as a positive feeling of going out and putting your talents to use is not easy and requires time, but can change the way you think about those habits in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final tool you can use to make habits more attractive, is the &lt;em&gt;motivation ritual&lt;/em&gt;. Every time you plan to engage in a desired habit, attach an activity you enjoy–and ritualise it. You can use this technique to create a cue from scratch–one user reported listening to music he enjoyed before getting focused on his writing. Eventually, the simple act of putting on his headphones, inspired his focus towards his work automatically. Adapt this to any situation, just remember to find something that makes you truly happy, and engage in that action &lt;em&gt;just before&lt;/em&gt; your desired habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end goal of course, is that the resultant habit also makes you feel happy, just like the chosen cue!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>anonymous</name><email>habitsblog1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Atomic Habits" /><summary type="html">Personal Context</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How the people around you shape your behaviour - Ch 9 Atomic Habits</title><link href="https://habitsblog.github.io/2019/05/20/atomic9/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How the people around you shape your behaviour - Ch 9 Atomic Habits" /><published>2019-05-20T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-05-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://habitsblog.github.io/2019/05/20/atomic9</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://habitsblog.github.io/2019/05/20/atomic9/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal Reflection&lt;/strong&gt;
Thinking back on my own experiences with the people around me–I realise that I have been subconsciously surrounding myself with people that promote active working habits. Informally, and on a more personal level, I tended to surround myself with people who were coincidentally both very friendly and hardworking. Remembering my time as a student in Delft, we often made for the library at 8.30 in busier times, staying for around 12 hours until 20.30, only to return home for a couple of beers as something of a nightcap/reward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a more formal note, one of the reasons I chose my next study programme in Maastricht had to do with the Problem-Based Learning approach (PBL), which focused on discussion groups rather than open lectures. A culture in which it was expected that you were well-read and prepared for every session and expected to contribute certainly boosted my study habits and allowed me to be more successful from an academic standpoint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are certainly myriad other habits that I have picked up from the people close to me, going anywhere from drinking coffee, to the inflection I use when saying “hello” at a certain point in my life! It’s fun to try and think of what they all might be, and who might be the originator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-role-of-family-and-friends&quot;&gt;The Role of Family and Friends&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section focuses on how culture and surrounding persons influence habit building, and the way we perceive certain activities and behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans have always been herd animals–in nomadic times, humans that stuck together had a higher chance of survival (for the most part.) Similar to our craving for fatty, salty, and sugary foods, we also have an innate desire to belong to part of a group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social norms&lt;/em&gt;, or the set of cultural standards by which a society operates, are like invisible guidelines that shape the way people behave, and thus the formation of their habits. Clear describes the three societal sub-groups whose habits we are most likely to imitate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The close&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The many&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The powerful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We explore the ways in which each of these groups offers opportunities to make habits more attractive, in line with the 2nd law of behaviour change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-close&quot;&gt;The close&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as we discussed earlier how a person’s direct environment shapes their habit, so do the persons that inhabit that direct environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study on partner fitness is referenced as an example; apparently a person is 57% more likely to become obese if their partner does so. The inverse is also true, although to a somewhat lesser degree (30%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a general rule, the closer you are to someone, the more likely you are to soak up their qualities or practices. Thus, it seems logical that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategy&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;“One of the most effective things you can do to build better habits is to join a culture where your desired behaviour is the normal behaviour.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Integrating yourself into a community where the norm is to part-take in a certain behaviour will make it all the more easier to engage in that behaviour yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make this even more powerful, you can join a culture where your desired behaviour is the norm, and you already have something in common with the group, e.g &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nerdfitness.com/&quot;&gt;nerd fitness&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-many&quot;&gt;The Many&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider Solomon Asch’s line experiment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/EJBkyTj.png&quot; alt=&quot;line experiment&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;color: gray; font-size: 80%; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Line (C) is the same length as the line on the first card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants are shown two cards, with a number of lines. There are many variations of this experiment, but in this one, participants were asked which of the three lines on the right card was most similar in length to the line on the left card (in this case C).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experiment was performed in a room, with the lines up for display to a whole group of people who had been instructed to all answer with one of the obviously &lt;em&gt;incorrect&lt;/em&gt; answers. What Asch found, was that as the group got large enough, the peer pressure led the test subject to forego the answer they knew to be right, and instead go along with the group. He also found that their likelihood to comply was significantly correlated with the size of the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to see how powerful this phenomena can be in shaping the behaviours of an individual–but there are some pitfalls to consider. Just as the participants in the test were pressured into giving the wrong answer in Asch’s line test, the behaviour you exhibit might not be optimal, the most efficient, or good at all. It is important to contextualise! Joining the tribe, and engaging in behaviours that are the norm, feels great–you’re conforming! Just remember that going against the grain might be even more difficult than doing it on your own..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-powerful&quot;&gt;The Powerful&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans are drawn towards behaviours that garner admiration, respect, approval, and status. Since times of old the respect and approval of the group has often resulted in better chance of survival, more attractive mate, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think about the self-help bookshelf at your local &lt;em&gt;parchmenterie&lt;/em&gt;, you will likely find yourself surrounded by the works of powerful industrialists, world-leaders, elite athletes, and renowned academics. In trying to achieve success ourselves, we try to imitate behaviours of people that society considers successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We seek to attain the same rewards garnered by the habits of those people, and thus strive to imitate their behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fixing-the-causes-of-bad-habits&quot;&gt;Fixing the Causes of Bad Habits&lt;/h2&gt;</content><author><name>anonymous</name><email>habitsblog1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Atomic Habits" /><summary type="html">Personal Reflection Thinking back on my own experiences with the people around me–I realise that I have been subconsciously surrounding myself with people that promote active working habits. Informally, and on a more personal level, I tended to surround myself with people who were coincidentally both very friendly and hardworking. Remembering my time as a student in Delft, we often made for the library at 8.30 in busier times, staying for around 12 hours until 20.30, only to return home for a couple of beers as something of a nightcap/reward.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dopamine and Temptation Bundling - Atomic Habits ch 7-8</title><link href="https://habitsblog.github.io/2019/05/17/atomic78/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dopamine and Temptation Bundling - Atomic Habits ch 7-8" /><published>2019-05-17T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-05-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://habitsblog.github.io/2019/05/17/atomic78</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://habitsblog.github.io/2019/05/17/atomic78/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The idea that a little bit of discipline would solve all our problems is deeply embedded in our culture.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal Context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quote above really hit me, in the sense that I’ve always been critical of my own sense of self-discipline. ‘How do I attain this unbreakable willpower and monk-level discipline to stay focused and achieve my goals?’ was a common self criticism that rang around in my head. The more I get a chance to break down how habits are structured and the triggers/cues that engage them work, I realise that everyone probably struggles with these kinds of thoughts to a certain degree. Finding a strategy that works for you is something probably almost everyone needs to do at some point in order to be more successful. My personal journey has been fraught with self deprecation towards this particular subject and I find it enlightening and relieving to encounter the topic discussed in this way. I have already started to bundle certain habits (coffee-morning wins), but am going to try and think of a way to help myself get focused when I start work. Integrating this phase of the day into a habit would greatly increase my productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-secret-to-self-control&quot;&gt;The Secret to Self Control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As evidenced and reinforced by research done on military heroin addicts, environment is a huge factor in determining the strength of a habit, even if it’s chemical. While culture often dictates a lack of discipline to come from an absence of willpower, evidence suggests that the people with the best self-control are in fact those who have to use it the least. Being smart with the way you position yourself within a context can have drastic impacts on how well you are able to make or break habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists refer to the self-feeding nature of bad habits with the term &lt;strong&gt;cue-induced wanting&lt;/strong&gt;. This essentially entails that an external trigger(&lt;strong&gt;cue&lt;/strong&gt;) causes a subconscious compulsive craving to repeat a bad habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though it’s possible to break bad habits, these cues are soo deeply ingrained that they are nigh impossible to remove. Finding yourself in the same environment years later, you might suddenly feel that pang to engage. Since maintaining iron willpower is nearly impossible in the long term, it is a far better strategy to manipulate your environment (as discussed in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://habitsblog.github.io/2019/05/16/atomic45/&quot;&gt;previous&lt;/a&gt; section). &lt;em&gt;Minimise access to the cue!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, referring to the first law of habit forming:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Good Habit&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bad Habit&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Make the cue obvious&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Make the cue invisible&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-make-a-habit-irresistible&quot;&gt;How to Make a Habit Irresistible&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Second law&lt;/strong&gt;: Make it attractive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly to how animals are ‘preloaded’ with certain behaviours (as demonstrated by Tinbergen’s bird-with-red-dotted-beak research), humans also react to certain stimulus subconsciously. These cues are known as &lt;em&gt;supernormal stimuli&lt;/em&gt;. Hunting for thousands of years has conditioned people to react a certain way to food high in salt, fat, and sugar–this means that even now, we go into something of a frenzy at the sight of a Big Mac. The modern food industry is just one of many that market products to appeal to this natural sense of craving, and further enhance it by making products more attractive in all sorts of ways(texture, colour, odour, etc)–they enhance the cue by &lt;em&gt;making it attractive&lt;/em&gt;, encouraging patrons to repeat the habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-craving&quot;&gt;What is craving?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to understand how to make a habit more attractive, or even triggered by a supernormal stimulus, we must understand craving, and the role of dopamine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dopamine is intrinsically interlinked with habits. Habits are a dopamine-driven feedback loop–the dopamine is what keeps you coming back. Rats who had their dopamine receptors blocked in experiments soon lost all interest in food, sex, and basically their will to live on the whole. While we often think of the dopamine release to be associated with engaging in the activity itself, it is important to note that dopamine is released also in &lt;strong&gt;anticipation&lt;/strong&gt; of the activity. &lt;em&gt;The reward system in your brain that is activated when you receieve the reward, is the same system that is activated when you anticipate the reward!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/bll8cAJ.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dopamine spike patterns&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;color: gray; font-size: 80%; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Dopamine spike patterns&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above you see how dopamine spikes manifest depending on the stage of habit formation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Dopamine is released when the reward is experienced for the first time&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;B&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The next time, dopamine is released in &lt;em&gt;anticipation&lt;/em&gt;. Since the reward is expected, dopamine spike is minimal&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;C&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;If you don’t receive the reward, you have a negative dopamine spike, because your expectations were subverted.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;D&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reward is provided, but later than expected.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These diagrams have a very important takeaway: &lt;strong&gt;desire is the engine that drives behaviour&lt;/strong&gt;. After the reward is known and expected, the dopamine largely comes in anticipation of the reward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;temptation-bundling&quot;&gt;Temptation bundling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This method of making habits more attractive relies on bundling an action that you want to do, with an action that you need to do. Without going into great detail, the idea behind this is that you’re more likely to find an initially unattractive behaviour attractive if you pair it with one of your favourite things to do. An classic example of this is watching a movie/series while running on the treadmill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This strategy can be further combined with &lt;a href=&quot;https://habitsblog.github.io/2019/05/16/atomic45/&quot;&gt;habit stacking&lt;/a&gt;, such that you can chain habits while tentation bundling for maximum effect, in the form:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After [current habit], I will [habit I need]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After [habit I need], I will [habit I want]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Temptation bundling is an excellent strategy to decrease the resistance towards a habit, by basically “softening the blow”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional note: The author made reference to Dutch Nobel prize-winning scientist Nikolaas Tinbergen, and I caught the last name as familiar; the only Dutch economist to ever win the Nobel prize was also named Tinbergen. As it turns out, they were brothers! Apparently, they also had a third brother, who didn’t win any Nobels–I wonder what the dinner table was like there at christmas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>anonymous</name><email>habitsblog1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Atomic Habits" /><summary type="html">“The idea that a little bit of discipline would solve all our problems is deeply embedded in our culture.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Manipulating Cues and Environments - Atomic Habits 5-6</title><link href="https://habitsblog.github.io/2019/05/16/atomic56/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Manipulating Cues and Environments - Atomic Habits 5-6" /><published>2019-05-16T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-05-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://habitsblog.github.io/2019/05/16/atomic56</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://habitsblog.github.io/2019/05/16/atomic56/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal Context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These chapters were all about habit building strategies centered around the first tenet of Clear’s doctrine, manipulating &lt;em&gt;cues&lt;/em&gt;. I was particularly intrigued by the habit-stacking strategy, in which one can essentially create a complete chain of behaviours. In previous meetings we had discussed what I see defined here as implementation intentions, something I think I would do well to try to apply–some of the positive habits that I have started to build rely on pure excitement and willpowere to maintain, and could use a bit more structure. I think about running for example, something that I like to do at the end of a long day, but happens spontaneously before or after dinner, and not exactly at a set time or on a specific day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The section on environment was interesting to read within the context of habits, as I had seen it before somewhat in behavioural economics texts describing “nudge” theory. One of the described notions that I had discovered on my own in past years was to separate your workspace from your personal space, something that is occasionally hard to do as a student living in one room. I do however notice how significantly different my mind operates in one environment or another. The cues surrounding me right now for example, are centered largely around leisure and relaxation–there is a guitar, there is a computer, a comfy sofa, and a little electronics project on the table–everything points towards downtime. While most of these objects serve one purpose, the computer for example is somewhat neutral. Once it has been designated for a certain role/habit however, it is hard to recontextualise. I know of myself that I am very sensitive to these environmental &lt;em&gt;cues&lt;/em&gt;, and that it is important for me to try and surround myself with environments that stimulate building of productive habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;two-habit-building-strategies&quot;&gt;Two Habit Building Strategies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Implementation Intentions&lt;/em&gt; - A statement expressing how and when you intend to implement a specific habit (proven to increase your likelihood to perform said action)
People who make a plan, will follow through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I will [behaviour] at [time] in [location].&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Habit Stacking&lt;/em&gt; - No behaviour happens in isolation (Diderot effect - lifestyle upgrades). One of the best ways to build a new habit is to identify a current habit, and stack your behaviour on top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;After [current habit], I will  [new habit]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combining habits, pairing them, bonding them, will make you more likely to assimilate the new one. The key is to use a habit that you already have deeply ingrained as the first link in the chain–eventually, as a master you will be able to create multi-habit combo stacks. Within the previous framework, the existing habit acts as the &lt;em&gt;cue&lt;/em&gt; for the new habit.
For optimal effectiveness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The cue should have the same frequency as the desired habit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The cue should be highly specific, and immediately actionable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can use &lt;em&gt;implementation intentions&lt;/em&gt; to make cues clearer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;environment-vs-motivation&quot;&gt;Environment vs Motivation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chapter is really interesting–a lot of “nudge” theory as to how your direct environment supports the development of new/breaking of old habits. (Recall the example about placement of healthy foods in school cafeterias from Thaler.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human beings perceive mostly the world empirically, through the use of our five senses–however, of the 11 million sensory receptors we possess, 10 million are dedicated to sight. “A small change in what you &lt;strong&gt;see&lt;/strong&gt; can lead to a big change in what you &lt;strong&gt;do&lt;/strong&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recall: Every habit is initiated by a cue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we are more likely to notice cues that stand out, we can initiate these habits more successfully by placing cues more accessibly. Sprinkling triggers throughout your surroundings helps you notice and think about your habit more often, and thus increases your chance of actuating the habit successfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting point–besides your own home (and even then) most of the world around us is structured by others, and often done to make you engage with your environment in a certain way. Changing your environment, this form of intrusion, is powerful because it isn’t something that people tend to do very often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-context&quot;&gt;On Context&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talked about triggers and surroundings previously, but it is important to realise that cues are contextual. Triggers are seldom individual cues, but rather the product of a surrounding with various sensory inputs–a context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider not what an object is, but what your relationship the object is. What does the object represent to you? The couch is where you like to read, the mirror is where you brush your teeth, but to someone else, these objects might represent something completely different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategically important&lt;/strong&gt;: Building a new habit can be much easier in a new environment, one in which the context is as yet undefined to you. A blank canvas is easier to start painting on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever possible avoid mixing the context of one habit with another! When you are mixing contexts, you are bound to try to mix habits, and the easier habit will win out. I know this from personal experience, unfortunately..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Relaxation is easier when you are in a space designed for that purpose. The same goes for working, sleeping, or any other manner of activity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>anonymous</name><email>habitsblog1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Atomic Habits" /><summary type="html">Personal Context</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hacking the habit process - Atomic Habits 3-4</title><link href="https://habitsblog.github.io/2019/05/13/atomic34/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hacking the habit process - Atomic Habits 3-4" /><published>2019-05-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-05-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://habitsblog.github.io/2019/05/13/atomic34</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://habitsblog.github.io/2019/05/13/atomic34/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The Conscious mind is the bottleneck of the brain”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever possible, your mind will strive to “pawn off” tasks to the unconscious brain. Since a habit is essentially just a behaviour that becomes automated, it is desirable to form good habits–so that you can have as many as possible life-improving and identity changing behaviours behave automatically. This in place of laying the task on your conscious brain, which takes significantly more effort. This provides you with more conscious freedom to expend wherever you see fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-process-of-building-a-habit&quot;&gt;The process of building a habit&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The habit building process as described by Clear can be divided in to four steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cue - Trigger your brain to initiate a behaviour. Basically, any kind of sensory input, activity, or something that can trigger a behavioural response. The cue is about &lt;strong&gt;noticing&lt;/strong&gt; the reward.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Craving - The motivational force behind every habit, the “&lt;strong&gt;why?&lt;/strong&gt;”. The craving is about &lt;strong&gt;wanting&lt;/strong&gt; the reward.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Response - The actual habit you form, the action that you perform in response to the cue. Objective of the response, is to achieve the reward. The response is about &lt;strong&gt;obtaining&lt;/strong&gt; the reward.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reward - Finally, the reward that is delivered by the response.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process constitutes a subconscious neurological feedback loop that you go through every time you perform a habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hacking-the-habit-process&quot;&gt;Hacking the habit process&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having introduced this process, Clear’s theory starts to come into play–his goal for the next sections is to try to elucidate how one might positively influence this process according to his methodology, in order to build &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; habits and break &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He mentions briefly the ways he views this, for each step of the habit forming process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Step&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Forming a good habit&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Breaking a bad habit&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Cue&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Make the cue obvious&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Make the cue invisible&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Craving&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Make the craving attractive&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Make the craving unattractive&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Response&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Make the response Easy&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Make the response difficult&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reward&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Make the reward satisfying&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Make the reward Unsatisfying&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These objectives are referred to by Clear as &lt;strong&gt;The Four Laws for Behaviour Change&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-first-law-make-it-obvious&quot;&gt;The first law: Make it obvious&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the habits that we have already ingrained, run automatically as described in the previous section. Clear refers to the “point and call” practice applied by Japanese train conductors–by explicitly calling out every step of the conductor’s safety protocol, they have significantly reduced human error. This same ideal applied to habit forming starts with the explicit identification of habits, be they good or bad. His suggested method for doing this is the habit scorecard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While not perfect, this method can provide you with a bit of a cursory overview as to daily habits and how you percieve them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, I noticed that I scored relatively few daily habits negative (-), but feel that the scorecard lacks a weighting system that effectively emphasises the effect of each habit–my negative habits often steal a lot of time and energy out of my day. While “browse the internet again” doesn’t seem very harmful, it sucks if that happens to take up a whole hour or more, without any sense of real satisfaction besides temporary relaxation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Habits Scorecard &amp;lt;/br&amp;gt;
Neutral (=)
Positive (+)
Negative (-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Habit&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Score&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wake up&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;=&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Check Phone&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Shower and get dressed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;=&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Podcast on (positive or negative, depending on entertainment or educational)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;=&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Make coffee&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;=&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Make (healthy) breakfast&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wins for the day&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Browse news &amp;amp; reddit&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brush teeth + Grooming&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pack Lunch&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Leave the house&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Cycle to University&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Set up workspace&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;=&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Browse internet again&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Make todo-list&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Get to work, pomodoros&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Groceries, on the way home&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;=&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;If time, relax for an hour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;=&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Cook dinner&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Watch TV, eat&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;=&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Run for 45-60, more podcasts&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Finish up tasks, if any left&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Get to bed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;=&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Browse internet, again&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><author><name>anonymous</name><email>habitsblog1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Atomic Habits" /><summary type="html">“The Conscious mind is the bottleneck of the brain”</summary></entry></feed>